Guide to the James Claude Thomson and James C. Thomson Jr. Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Slides, 1948-1949; 1949; Series V
  - Metal box containing slides of China and Hong Kong; slide carousel #4 containing slides of Peking, Great Wall of China, Summer Palace, Western Hills, etc., circa 1949 (Box 7, Folder 157)
  - Slides of Iran: peoples of Shiraz, Isfahan, other sites in Iran, labeled and unlabeled slide boxes, 1951, 1952, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 158)
  - Slides of Japan: Inoshima, Kamakca, Bentenjima, Uji-Yamada, Nojiri, Hokkaido, labeled slide boxes, 1953, 1954, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 159)
  - Slides of Korea: Palace and Secret Garden, country trip, Nan San Han Shan trip, city scenes of Seoul, Autumn in the Secret Garden, Seoul, and slides of Swat, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 160)
  - Slides of Iran: carousel tray #1, Persia, WHO, Beirut, Damas, Tehran, Qum, Isfahan; carousel tray #2, Persia, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 161)
  - Slides of Iran and Herat, Afghanistan in a carousel slide tray, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 162)
  - Slide boxes labeled China, Japan, Iran, Persia, Korea, HK (Box 13, Folder 163)
- Films, 1928-1957; Series VI
  - Thomson family: four 3 1/2 inch, 16mm reels (1928-1933); twelve 2 3/4 inch 16mm reels (mostly family footage - see list of reels in Box 18, Folder 169), 1928-1957 (Box 14, Folder 164)
  - Thomson family: one 5 inch 16mm reel:#1)"Jimmy and family in USA, 1931-1933"; five 7 inch 16mm reels:2)"Summer trip to USA, 1931"; 3)"Jimmy, Princeton, 1931"; 4)"DAR Picnic, 1941"; 5)"Jim, Cambridge, 1954"; 6)"Heath/ South Kent, 1956", 1931-1956 (Box 15, Folder 165)
  - Thomson family / Nanking footage: three 3 1/2 inch 16mm reels: #1) "Nanking, Christmas at Mills, 1930"; 2)"Sun Yat-sen memorial, MIng tombs, etc. 1930 or 1931"; 3) "John's party, Hillcrest track meet, our house and University buildings - Nanking, 1931", 1930-1931 (Box 16, Folder 166)
  - Thomson family / Nanking footage: three 4 3/4 inch 16 mm reels:# 4) "Dr. Bowen, Robin Hood - Nanking, 1929"; 5) "The trip from SG to Honolulu, Nanking and Hillcrest, 1933"; 6) "Hillcrest and Nancy's Commencement, Shanghai American School, Lotus Lake, Purple Mountain -1936", 1929-1936 (Box 16, Folder 166)
  - Thomson family/ Nanking footage: four 2 3/4 inch 16mm reels: #7) "Nanking, 1933 - Emily C??"; 8) "Kuling, Nanking - swimming, camping, 1934"; 9) "Kuling, 1934"; 10)"Nanking, 1934 - Lotus Lake, Sun Yat-sen tomb, family", 1933-1934 (Box 16, Folder 166)
  - Footage mostly of Nanking: nine 7 inch 16mm reels: #1) "Fall 1930 -Nanking"; 2) "Winter 1930 - Nanking, family, Ginling College, rural scenes, city walls, New Year scenes"; 3) "Nojiri?/ Nanking - 1930"; 4) "China Diary -1930-1931"; 5) "Hangchow, Chinkiang, Niagara - 1931"; 6) "Ginling"; 7) "Ginling College - Winter 1931"; 8) "Summer 1933 - Trip to China"; 9) "Unzen, our garden, Lotus Lake, Hillcrest Fair - 1935", 1930-1935 (Box 17, Folder 167)
  - Footage mostly of Nanking/ China: ten 7 inch 16mm reels: #1) "Nanking - 1935"; 2) "Hillcrest, Shanghai American School - 1936"; 3) "Nanking, Peking, Summer Palace, Ming Tombs, Great Wall, Shanghai - 1937-1938"; 4) print of #3; 5) "Nanking, Shanghai, Hanoi, Hong Kong - 1938"; 6) "Nojiri - 1938"; 7) "Shanghai American School - 1938-1939"; 8) "Nojiri - 1939"; 9) "Mt. Rest, Smith - 1942 ?SAS Commencement 1939?"; 10) "Unzen - 1954", 1935-1954 (Box 18, Folder 168)
  - Peggy Thomson's catalogue of the slides/film contained in the collection; catalogue by J.C. Thomson of the China slides; historical notes on Peking by Margaret Seabury Thomson, the wife of J.C. Thomson (Box 18, Folder 169)
  - Handwritten notes of J.C. Thomson on index cards, concerning the history of Iran and the sites of the slides he took; another series of handwritten notes concerning sites in Herat, Afghanistan and Iran which he captured on film; handwritten notes concerning China and Iran (Box 18, Folder 170)
  - Use copies of the films contained in boxes 16 - 18 (2 VHS tapes, 2 DVDs); "China Films Archive Tape 1" (DVCam) (Box 19, Folder 171)
- Addendum - 2003, Series VII
  - Correspondence
    - JCT with son James Claude Thomson, Jr (JCT, Jr.), 1940 - 1949 Jun (Box 20, Folder 172)
    - JCT with JCT, Jr., 1949 Jul - 1950 (Box 20, Folder 173)
    - JCT with JCT, Jr., 1951 (Box 20, Folder 174)
    - JCT with JCT, Jr., 1952-1953 (Box 20, Folder 175)
    - JCT with JCT, Jr., 1954-1955 (Box 20, Folder 176)
    - JCT with JCT, Jr., 1956-1969 (Box 20, Folder 177)
    - JCT with JCT, Jr., n.d. (Box 20, Folder 178)
    - JCT letters to other family members, 1940-1979 (Box 20, Folder 179)
    - Letters to/from others (Box 20, Folder 180)
  - Personal Items and Memorabilia
    - Postcards, calling card, etc. (Box 20, Folder 181)
    - Diary of JCT - Rotary Club Book, Nanking, 1934 (Box 20, Folder 182)
    - Travel document from Ministry of Finance, Yunnan; visas of JCT and MCT (Box 20, Folder 182, 183)
    - Obituaries of JCT, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 183)
- Addenda - 2009, 2015, 1937-2010
  - Correspondence
    - JCT letters to family from Nanking, 1937 Aug-Oct (Box 21, Folder 1,2)
    - JCT letters to family while traveling, 1938 May-Jul (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Margaret Thomson general letter from Nanking, written to Presbyterian Church in Plainfield, NJ, which supported the Thomson family, 1936 Nov (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - JCT, Jr. to sister and general letter, 1988 Oct - 1994 Jun (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Writings, speeches
    - Margaret Thomson talk given to travel club, 1941 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - JCT, Jr: Book review of The Great Chinese Revolution; Op-Ed: "The Day Pearl Buck and the Nobel Committee shocked the world"; Article for GBH re. Tiananmen massacre, 1987-1989 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - JCT, Jr: "Jilted Again"; "One Historian's Lament", 1989, 1991 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - JCT, Jr: Address at Pearl S. Buck Centennial Symposium at Randolph-Macon College, 1992 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - JCT, Jr: "Pearl Buck and the American Quest for China"; "Pearl Buck at One Hundred"; "A Fragile Relationship", 1992 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - "The Actress and the Novelist"; "Five Years Later"; fragments, 1992-1994 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - John Seabury Thomson: "The Role of the MIssionary Teachers of Science in China", 1984 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Personal Items and Memorabilia
    - Obituaries and remembrances of JCT, Jr. by his sisters and colleagues, 2002 (Box 21, Folder 12,13)
    - Remembrances of JCT, Jr. by his sisters and colleagues, 2002 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Obituaries and remembrances of JCT, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Photographs of JCT and JCT, Jr. (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Collected Material
    - Typescript material related to the Rape of Nanking, including "Note on Aftermath of Registration at the University" by M. Searle Bates (19937 Dec 26); transcript of article from Hein Shun Pao "Disastrous Fire at the Soviet Embassy Nanking" (1938 Jan 6); transcript of article from Sin Shun Pao "Japanese Troops Gently Soothe the Refugees" (1938 Jan 8); "Notes on the Immediate Situation as Affecting the University of Nanking" with cover letter to American Embassy, by M. Searle Bates (1938 Jan 8); letter to "Dear Friends" from M. Searle Bates (1938 Jan 10); articles from New York Times "At the Rape of Nanking: A Nazi Who Saved Lives" (1996 Dec 12), 1937 Dec - 1939 Jan, 1996 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous, including excerpt from My Several Worlds by Pearl Buck, 1987-1989 (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - Recording of program about Pearl Buck, "East Wind/ West Wind", includes participation of John and Jim Thomson (DVD), 1993 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - "Sketches of Nanking - Papers of the Literary Department of the Nanking Woman's Club" - 1922-1923 edition and enlarged, revised 1933 edition, 1923, 1933 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - My Nanking Home 1918-1937 - memoir by Nancy Thomson Waller, 2010 (Box 22, Folder 3)